body
science
I am
attention again
searching
package
laughs
anymore
so we finished explaining uh how three
different groups of things don't have
any nature of their own and we started
with the
so the lack of a definitive uh
self-natural definite nature of having
some kind of characteristics the way the
Buddha called it uh with regard to
things which were what was the first one
good thought uh construct right and then
we went on to the second one which is to
prove that there was no nature of having
started with regard to things which are
dependent or come from causes or other
conditions and then we approved a lack
of nature of ultimate of being ultimate
with regard to two of the groups which
was uh with regard to
dependent things and with regard to
Young dupe or the empty things emptiness
itself okay so those are the three uh
those three descriptions of uh things
that don't have a nature have already
been finished
that's a kind of a review of what we did
yesterday
then as you recall yesterday evening we
talked about uh some kind of slight
misconception that the omnising your
number hand and we're going to go back
to that remember we just introduced it
and now we're going to go back and
explain it in more details
foreign
um
who is it foreign
sometimes
um
uh he's gonna look for a a reference
while I'm Translating that he's looking
for uh so we go on to Justin Copper's
reputation of omniscient General uh uh
janamba's idea that remember what it was
yesterday uh Jesso Kappa is expressing
the uh position that uh emptiness or
young to what we call a total existence
or something like that is the exact
flip-flop is the exact opposite of a
self-existent thing and not just
something which is other than that and
then the number says that's I don't like
that way of interpreting it because uh
when you when you think of emptiness you
think of a positive object in the same
way that you do when when you think of a
vase so I think everything should be a
positive thing and not a negative thing
it's not a simple absence of something
it's a presence of something and this is
a very uh famous misperception
misconception then Jetson Kappa uh tries
he uses two different scriptural uh
authorities to show
number that this is incorrect the first
one is from itself from the book in
which the Buddha explains what he meant
when he taught his other books okay and
in that one it says he specifically says
in here it's uh page 14. uh line eight
something like that seven nine seven he
uses the expression uh
I mean and the most important word here
is some some means simple in the
expression simple lack of something or
the simple absence of something so he
says the Lord Buddha is using this same
language he doesn't say positive thing
or a positive uh thing he's saying it's
a simple lack of something so the word
simple is the one that uh points out to
your number and says look this is the
most important word here this this is
referring to the idea of emptiness being
a simple absence or a simple lack of
something and not a positive object then
uh Jensen copper goes on to point out an
illustration in Scripture that the Lord
Buddha himself uses to describe
emptiness and he says it's like space
it's like space and in tibetan the word
for space is and that also means sky so
instead because guess a lot is careful
to point out that when we say in space
we don't mean the sky you know when I
say Nam or namka I don't I'm not
referring to this blue thing out here
space means the simple absence of
obstruction so uh what we mean by the
word space is that the simple lack or
simple absence of something so the
Buddha himself used that as an
illustration to demonstrate how how
emptiness is so the Buddha himself is
using a simple lack or a simple absence
of something as an illustration of
emptiness so Lord so Jason copper says
to your number the Buddha himself in
both a scriptural Authority from the
explanation of what the sutras mean and
in another scriptural Authority where he
Compares emptiness to empty space or a
simple lack of of obstruction he says in
those two references the Buddha is
clearly saying that it's a simple
absence of something a simple lack of
something and not a positive object
foreign
from the top uh he says it comes from
the same book uh I'm sorry uh yeah from
the explanation and meaning of the
sutras and uh he says
uh this is how it is I'll give you an
example uh space itself is a simple lack
of obstructible form uh and that's what
sets it off that's that's it is a simple
absence it is a it is a
means like a simple uh lack of something
okay
devoid of something and then he he says
that's exactly the way in which I want
to describe to you uh the lack of self
to things that's exactly the same way it
is and then so there's the example
itself
so uh from from this description that
you find on page 15 from the previous
description on page 14 it's obvious that
uh emptiness or what we call Total
existence or young to uh that it is a it
is a simple lack of the self-existence
of things and it's and it's a simple
flip-flop from a self-existing thing
which doesn't exist that the simple
absence of that a simple lack of that is
what Young dip or emptiness is
better make a mark on that last part
because uh we're gonna come to something
later on that might give us a headache
like we had yesterday on this one okay
um
foreign
for those of you who know Tibetan page
14 line five
this is where a hassle a big hassle is
going to come later so you might want to
even Mark your make a little Mark the
mental note or middle note in your notes
that page 14 line five uh in on that
line uh Lord Buddha describes the third
group right the the mind only school's
third Group which is uh called total
existence or something we have to find a
better translation when we get to a
better description of it but that that
is described as the lack of a
self-nature
to things which are uh do chain duche
means has a couple meanings but in this
case in the Sutra the word means factors
in the sense of a cause something which
brings about something else that's
called a duche uh and those are always
changing things okay so you have to
realize that you have to be sensitive to
the fact that when the Buddha describes
emptiness or young in the third category
he's describing it as the lack of self
to things which act as causes okay then
when Judson copper gets to explaining it
which is on page 14 uh the eighth line
from the bottom he says that thing which
Lord Buddha is pointing out as empty
when he describes the third category
which is emptiness or in total existence
or something like that that thing which
he is describing as being empty is all
things which have been produced okay
which it which is more like the past
tense of producing you see when the
Buddha describes it as the lack of
self-nature he says the lack of
self-nature of things which are act as
causes or act as factors when then when
Jetson copper gets to explaining it he
says the Buddha takes as his
as the object which is empty all those
things which have been produced okay
using the past tense then I asked that's
it if the point is that those two
words aren't present tense and past
tense you know agent and and result and
he said that's not the main point here
because really those cover the same
objects but the big question here will
come about of why do they take changing
things or caused things or even causes
which are all the same category they're
all the same group of stuff why do they
take all those as being what it is which
is explained as being empty and when you
say that those don't have a self you
arrive at group number three okay the
fact that Lord Buddha has taken this
group as being the thing which is empty
of self-existence in order to get the
third group is significant and there's
going to be a hassle about it later
foreign
uh you you uh as I recall you you accept
that this particular Sutra meaning the
Sutra in which the Buddha explains the
intent of his other sutras right uh as
being which means literal right remember
what we're talking about the whole book
right what's literally what's figurative
he says as I remember you believe that
this particular Sutra is little right he
has to say yes I believe it's literal
meaning I have to take it on face value
whatever it says I have to take it
literally and not I I can't interpret it
as something else whatever if I accept
that this suture is literal then I have
to say that the precise wording here is
what the Buddha really meant and I'm not
allowed to interpret it into something
else so then he says and here we have
two specific uh references in the book
that you say is literal first where the
Buddha says that uh emptiness or or what
we're calling total existence is the
simple reverse or the simple absence of
the ultimate self-existent thing which
is what we call Parts okay the
self-existence of Dharma means the
self-existence of your parts as opposed
to suffixes of Youth so when we refer to
the self-existence of objects remember
that that means mainly uh the parts of
yourself as opposed to yourself so he
says remember that we've all agreed that
the self-existence of objects the lack
of that and the this book says is what
the third group is first of all second
of all in the example that the Buddha
used in the in his description of empty
space as being a good example for
emptiness he kept using the word some
all throughout here is use the word
sound which means simple simple meaning
implying simple absence of something
simple lack of something so he says uh
you're first of all on one hand you're
accepting that this Sutra is literal and
then on the other hand you're saying oh
but Emptiness is a positive thing
self-standing positive thing it's a
discrete positive object you know so
you're on one hand you're accepting that
Emptiness is a discrete positive object
on the other hand you're accepting that
this Sutra is literal and this Sutra
says that emptiness is a simple lack of
something so you are completely
contradicting yourself you have no feet
to stand on your position is wiped out
okay
oh
you need it
anymore foreign
remember that we described emptiness of
the third group in the mine only school
as being the simple lack or the the
reverse of a self-existent thing the
gotcha the thing that we deny uh and and
that we've just established with the
genoma for example that it is the simple
lack or the simple absence of the thing
which we deny but remember that there's
a difference between how the mind only
School identifies identifies the thing
that emptiness is empty of and there's a
difference in the way that the middle
way School explains how uh what the
thing is that emptiness is empty of so
so obviously yondu or or emptiness
itself according to each school is going
to be different why because the thing
that they deny the thing that emptiness
is empty of they have different ways of
identifying that so Jetson cop is going
to go on to say that look you mind only
school people you don't really know how
to how to identify the thing which is
self-existing correctly because and then
that leads you to misidentify what
Emptiness is because m
that total existence thinks is the
reverse or the absence of that thing so
that so you don't know how to establish
uh really what the third Group is
because you don't know how to establish
clearly what the thing is that we deny
when we speak of emptiness not having
something
foreign
so here's the very key at this this
point the key here the is the crucial
point is that the identification of what
Emptiness is empty of the identification
of what it is that we deny it differs
between the mind only school and the
middle way school and that's the and
that's the key here uh the mind only
school is saying that uh they do
describe an emptiness they do describe
an emptiness for example of a water
pitcher they do say that it's that it's
the lack of of that self nature of the
water pitcher but the way in which they
describe the thing which they deny uh
will be will be talked about much more
later that's coming much more later how
they specifically identify the thing it
is that we say emptiness is empty out
going to higher school they are they are
describing it as the lack of any
definitive nature or the lack of any
nature of existing by definition uh they
use the same wording so but what it
means in the mighty Mika school what it
means in the middle way school for
something to Exist by definition is
something totally different and at this
point Jason cup is saying you mine only
School even though we haven't identified
how they identify even though we haven't
described yet precisely how they
identify the thing that doesn't exist
that we're denying uh
he's still saying at this point you
don't know how to identify it correctly
now why why that is how the news is
going to come later
here it is
we haven't yet really gotten into
clearly what the object that the is the
not what what the object which you deny
when we speak of emptiness is for the
Minor League school now at this point in
our class you guys are starting to get
some kind of uh feeling or some kind of
instinct that how they identify it and
how the mind how the middle way
identifies it must be different you've
got a clear feeling that uh there must
be some Booboo here you know there must
be some discrepancy about how they
identify when emptiness is empty of and
how the middle way describes how what
emptiness is empty of although I haven't
we haven't gone through in specific
detail how the mine only School
identifies what it is that emptiness is
empty of what a self-existent thing
would be like but anyway the Point here
only the only Point here is that you
start getting a feeling or sensitivity
to the fact that they're going to
identify them differently
foreign
language uh like in your system or
according to you or this is the way that
you guys uh positive and the implication
there is that he doesn't accept it and
then later on he's going to be uh
describing to you a different system
which is his own system which is the
middleweight system so uh points out
that throughout this section and
especially in these last few lines uh
when Jason copper is saying that's how
you guys uh describe it that's how you
guys establish it this is your system
that by implication he's he's saying my
system's coming later I believe in the
mining Mika system that's the right
system and you're going to get this
system later
than it is
for example if you have a person who is
wandering around India and he meets
other people and he's always saying to
them oh uh you're uh Indian aren't you
or oh you have to bet not you you know
are you from this country uh India right
anyone who goes around saying that is
automatically implying that they're not
from India you see what I mean they're
implying that they are that there are
some other kind of people some other
kind of Nations people so it's the same
thing here just a cop is going around
saying oh you believe done yeah you
believe that yeah oh your position is
that right and the implication is
exactly the same that's not my belief
that's not my system
I don't know um
this is
foreign foreign
um
foreign
you know and implying that I am from
that system uh if you want to know if in
the in the final end in the in the final
final end of this whole book you know
what Justin copper is going to say is
his belief system because don't forget
that all through this book you know all
those pages he will have described all
of the beliefs of the Mind only school
on these questions and then he will have
described all the beliefs of the middle
way school and all these questions and
then at the very end of the book which I
hope you guys get to someday uh here's
his uh final position on what country
he's from you know what person he is uh
page 287
uh it's about one two three four five
six seven eight eight lines down and uh
Judson Kappa says
let's ask a question now and yes points
out that he's asking a question to
himself this is like a rhetorical
question okay so jezzo Kappa is asking a
question to Judson Kappa
um and and the the lines here say now we
have seen in the text that you've
written how uh the idea of what is
literal and what is figurative and how
to distinguish between the two is
covered or is treated in the great two
systems meaning uh the great systems of
the two great innovators meaning the
mine only School in the middle way
school and then uh there are gone back
now we have seen uh how different people
you've gone through how many many
different people even among the mind
only school and even among the
middleweight school for example in the
swatantrica the the independent group uh
the lower part of the madimika you've
described in detail all the different
divisions all the different ways that
people look upon the question of how to
distinguish between what is literal and
what is figurative and uh among all
those there are two uh gondel Kimbo
means uh uh in this case Kimball
normally means an Abbott or the person
who gives you your monastic vows so here
it just means Big Shot you know big men
so the two big men of who are trying to
explain what the Buddha meant when he's
talking about uh this is what I really
meant in the scriptures in that book
okay uh so uh there are there are many
people who follow either one or the
other of them there are many ways of
describing what is figurative and what
is little and now please at the very end
can you tell me which one do you choose
to follow you know which one of these
two uh great innovators or which one of
these two great systems are you Jetson
copper which one do you claim to follow
okay and then he says Tina means if you
ask me that question uh then he breaks
off into this beautiful poetry his
answer to himself he breaks off into
these beautiful lines of poetry okay and
it's and it's something like
you know I must admit that from the very
depths of my heart I have infinite
respect for all the eloquent words of
all the great Masters Buddhist Masters
who have ever come in this world you
know so first he starts off by saying
you know my in my heart deep in my heart
I have total respect and love for all
the incredible teachings of all the
great Buddhist Masters who have ever
come in this world
um
uh but John okay but okay there is a
system where uh they use a very very
beautiful explanation of dependent
origination what it means for something
to be dependent and they base everything
on this explanation what it means for
something to be dependent and they use
that reasoning to destroy all our
Tendencies to see things that
self-existent so he says there's one
system that uses that method very
effectively uh that is
uh it says uh we can open that Mighty
make a door a little bit okay uh just
that when we get to these verses you can
you can peek in there a little bit okay
this is sort of uh in tibetanus tender
means a very auspicious to go to the end
and let you peek in at the end and peek
in at the system of the money making and
it's just suspicious that you'll end up
being there okay so then he says
there's one system that uses dependent
origination to destroy all our
Tendencies to hold things in
self-existent now we're on the page 288
and that is the the beautiful cool
Moonlight that comes from China and
Chandra means moon right so uh he's the
great uh explainer of the middle way uh
in the books that we use in the
monastery so you're you're a Moonlight
uh has come down and the open opened the
eyes of my uh kundal kunda is a kind of
a Lotus or kind of a rare flower that
only blooms at night so this is a
beautiful exam you know he's saying uh
the eyes my eyes my kunda Lotus night
night flowering eyes have been opened by
the Moonlight referring to Chandra cutie
okay and uh and I've I've laid eyes now
I've been able to see the path set forth
by him and by Buddha palita who
explained chandigaretti okay and so uh
having seen this anyone who's had that
Moonlight come down to their eyes and
see that way and that unique path which
uses dependent origination it good a
deep interpretation of dependency Nation
not just oh things come from their
causes and their conditions but somebody
who explains it in the ultimate way that
the process does meaning projections
right so anyone who's seen that path in
that Moonlight and had their eyes open
in that way then
you'd be who where could you ever find
anybody who wouldn't follow uh Ariana's
system once they'd seen all that uh so
it says
that's my answer
okay that's my answer to your question
whose question Jessica's own answer to
himself question to himself
uh since we skipped to the back of the
book don't go mixing up the mind only
score here okay I mean take your mind
out of my knowing school and don't
forget that these words are being spoken
from a totally different viewpoint
the only reason I skipped to the back of
the book and gave you this particular
section is that I wanted you to
appreciate Jason kappa's you know making
us as what they call it aspirations
uh aspersions
it's called aspersions in English like
he's saying that's their system this is
how they describe it this is what they
think you know and and I wanted to make
it clear to you that what Justin copper
is doing here in those uh in those
oblique references is that that's not my
system I got my own system and and here
his his description of what he believes
the system is so I just wanted to take
you from mine only his saying that's the
mine only school that's what they think
to the back where he says and here's
what I this is if you ask me what system
I am here's the system I am okay I think
you know and and I wanted to make it
clear to you that what Justin copper is
doing here in those uh in those oblique
references is that that's not my system
I got my own system and and here his his
description of what he believes the
system is so I just wanted to take you
from mine only his saying that's the
mine only school that's what they think
to the back where he says and here's
what I this is if you ask me what system
I am here's the system I am okay
uh
nowadays in the world mine only school
is very popular especially among the
Western Scholars and I've had people
come in my room and say gentle kappa's
real Viewpoint is my only school he
doesn't that's what Justin copper really
believes and I say no he didn't and I
stick this in their face and I say look
this is what he said and he didn't say
that he said he's money Mika and and I
use that nowadays for all those people
who who are going around saying that you
know the real true teaching is the minor
miscope it is yeah
you might have a tendency as a western
Buddhist or just normal Buddhist and say
some people come to you and say oh some
scholar comes up to you and says oh the
teaching of uh gentle Kappa is really
mine only school what what Justin copper
really believed in with the mind only
school and then you might uh be you
might have this tendency to say that oh
no no he was the great he was the
wonderful Jason Kappa he's our great
rude llama of our tradition you know he
couldn't have been he must have been in
my Jamaica prosecutor he must have been
the highest Money Maker school you know
and I don't want you to answer like that
that's a dumb way to answer that's
that's not how we should answer that
question somebody comes up to you and
says that jezon Kappa believes in mine
only school or he represents minority
school I want you to stick this
reference in their face you know and say
look it says in his book he says that's
not my system what I am is mighty making
processing geek I follow China I follow
that's my system
this is
that was a cookie that I gave you as a
treat and now we're going back to the
main text
you're a special cookie because he likes
cookies
uh the next section is section number
three is an illustration these are
illustrations to illustrate the truth of
how those three groups of things lack in
the uh self nature so we got through
saying that uh nominal things uh when
you call it we've been calling it
constructs uh don't have any uh nature
of their own they don't have any nature
of being what was it of having
characteristics the Lord Buddha said and
then when he got on to things then had
are dependent things that come from
their causes then he said that they
don't have any nature of growing and
then when he got on to things emptiness
itself which were calling total
existence or something like that doesn't
have any nature of being what was the
third name
uh ultimate of being ultimate so so
those were the three statements that
Lord Buddha made that's how he covered
those three groups and now we're going
to get an illustration that will help us
understand what you know that fact
there'll be some kind of metaphor or
some kind of concrete illustration that
will help us remember what those three
are
foreign
uh the three examples that are used for
the three groups of the minoli school
are coming up are uh the first one uh is
uh what we call constructs and the
example here is what we call a flower
that grows in mid-air like no dirt no
water no nothings just starts to grow
there in the middle of in the mid-air
okay that's the first example that's the
example for constructs which is the
first of the three groups the example
for the second one is uh something like
uh magic show or illusion for example
gesla says a movie for example the
reality the relative reality of a movie
is an example for number two and then
the example for number three which we've
already mentioned uh the example for
emptiness is empty space itself space
itself it could be translated as place
maybe okay but space itself
uh we already finished explaining the
the third example for for emptiness
right we already explained the space one
foreign
uh when we talk about a flower that
grows in mid-air as being a good example
of something which is uh a construct
don't uh we're talking about the quality
that a flower that grows in mid-air has
that uh if you it's existence it's only
existence is as an imagined object okay
so it's just something that you have
imagined that you have created in your
imagination so the point here is that
the point of the illustration here is
that a flower that could just appear in
midair without any dirt no water no seed
could just Boom come out in mid-air uh
is an example the point here is that
it's an example of something which is
imaginary something which has been
created in your mind and is projected
out there and whose only existence is in
your own mind the minute you tell
somebody the word flower that grows in
midair they do have some kind of mental
image of something growing in mid-air
and so that's the main point here that
there's some kind of uh coming from the
mind that it's created by your own
imagination and that's the point of it
here now there's another quality of
flowers that go in midair that's that
they don't exist at all they have no
existence at all and oftentimes they're
used to illustrate something which has
no existence at all but that's not the
point here okay so it's not Point here
that we're using a flower that grows in
midair as an example for something that
doesn't exist at all the point here is
that from the mind only point of view
here is an object which does exist
but which it does not have any unique
existence from its own side which is how
they're kind of defining concrete
reality right something that's out there
and has its own uh way of being unique
way of being from its own side and not
dependent on me so here we have a
totally different category of stuff uh
constructs are are something that exist
only uh as something that exists by
virtue of our imagination by virtue of
our mental images so please don't
confuse it here uh with the other places
where it's used as an example for
something that doesn't have any
existence at all that's not the point at
all the point here is that the first
group of stuff which is called
constructs is similar to a flower that
grows in mid-air in that it's simply a
creation of our minds of our imagination
thank you foreign
foreign
produced
uh in the text here uh they get on to
the second example which is that cause
things are exemplified by uh by an
illusion or by a magic show or by
something which is imaginary illusory uh
something kind of an illusion or some
kind of deception like a movie or a
magic trick or something like that think
of a magic trick so the how is it that
uh things which are caused are described
by the mind only school as being similar
to a magic trick just uncomfort said
I'll tell you about it later I'll
explain it later guess what it says I'll
explain it to you now okay so uh how it
happens is this uh in the mind only
school they believe that um
that uh by the way we're talking about
all cost things so guess a lot says we
can't really describe how every cost
thing in the universe is like a magic
trick let's take one cause thing to be
the representative and he is a joke in
tibetan meaning the government
representative uh the legally elected
representative of all uh changing things
so all changing things in the word
Universe all functional things in the
universe are going to be represented by
this one guy named Vape or water pitcher
okay so water pitcher is going to be our
example how is it that a water pitcher
is like a magic trick according to the
mind only School in the mind only School
remember that they think their main
thing about this is that the water
pitcher and the eye the eye
Consciousness which perceives the water
pitcher okay the the the the the the
Seer of the water pitcher and the water
pitcher itself are are coming from or
what we call one substance they have
they are made of one thing
means they are made of the same stuff
okay so in the Minor League school they
say that the water pitcher and the state
you know the the visual consciousness of
the water pitcher are made of the same
stuff and in this school made of the
same stuff has a unique meaning it means
that they come from one block chart or
one mental seed so there's one mental
seed which when it ripens is producing
both of the water pitcher and the the
visual consciousness of the water
pitcher now does it seem to that way to
us does it seem that way to us on a
normal basis you know do we go around
saying oh look uh there's a water
pitcher which has been created by one
comic seed which has also created my
perception of the water pitcher you know
do we do we think that normally do you
go around saying that he says well no
you don't now you go around thinking
that there's a water pitcher out there
totally separate from me I'm over here
I'm not the water pitcher I the
perceiver and the water pitcher are two
different totally different things this
is by the way in the in the school that
precedes the mind only school which is
called the sutrist school the second of
the four schools they say that the main
main trip going on here is that the
water pitcher is actually the cause or
one of the conditions for the arrival of
the perception of the water pitcher but
here in the mine only School the take is
a little bit different it's one karmic
seed producing simultaneously in a way
the the thing which you are perceiving
and the thing which is perceiving it but
it doesn't look that way to you does it
I mean to a normal person it looks like
that's out there I'm over here that
couldn't be being produced by the same
seed that I'm being produced by so
there's an illusion here there's a
illusion here the way it is and the way
it seems to be are different
the mind is is taking something which
really is there which means the fact
that they're both coming from the same
karmic seed and saying that's not there
and when the mind says that something
that really is there is not there then
you have what we call an illusion but
then you have what we call a deception
and and the mind is being full so in the
in the mind only school this is what
they mean when they say cause things or
functional things are like a an illusion
or like a magic trick that's the main
point that's being that's being that's
the main point of the example when you
say that cost things or functional
things are like an illusion or like a
magic trick okay a little bit tough okay
okay
don't forget the Johnson copper said
I'll explain this later and uh hopefully
uh in this class if we get that far
we'll get to that later too so I suggest
you make a little Mark here and say this
is something that Justin copper said he
was going to get to later and it's my
hope who knows that we can get that far
and we'll actually get to the point
where he starts to discuss that
oh
thank you foreign
here on the last line of page 15 uh in
the first half of the last line there he
says
I'll tell you about later why cause
things are similar to a magic trick and
there is finished with that one that's
where he actually says then then he goes
on to say uh La Means whereas
the meaning of the the example that was
given for emptiness right the third
group uh
means you can get that uh it's a natural
outflow Q means Q means like an outflow
or a stream or a bridge and he says
that's a natural outflow from the Sutra
that you just had uh and between the
last line of page 15 and the upper part
of page 15 uh the Buddha himself has
given empty space as an example and
Justin Kappa is saying look you can get
that the your understanding that Sutra
is a natural outflow of reading that
Central I don't have to go and explain
to you Stephanie you just teach what I
just gave you and it'll just come
automatically in a steady flow the
meaning will come to you from that I'm
not going to treat that separately what
does the Buddha say in that section I
guess it keeps again that empty space is
the simple absence of anything which
would block something and in the same
way emptiness itself or that third
category total existence or whatever you
want to call it is a simple absent of
this of a
to the parts of a personal two objects
and that's and that's a simple app so
when you got that from
absent simple lack of something simple
fact that something is not there uh
actually and I don't have to go into any
bigger explanation about it
foreign
nature of existing by definition if you
just do it that simply if you cover all
three with that single characterization
in the mind only School you'd have a
problem he only used that wording with
the first group which is uh imaginary
things or constructed thing so he says
if you use that
if that that specific wording uh is is
kind of reserved in the minority school
for the first group and if you use that
wording to describe what they mean when
the Buddha said they don't have any
nature which he did say for all three
groups if he used those words to
describe what it means not to have any
nature you're going to get in trouble in
the mind only within the mind on this
girl
um
uh so uh
and only score don't forget you are not
allowed to go to that other door through
to the money maker school I'm going to
ask you a mine only school question in
the mind-only school if they
characterize the meaning of things don't
have any nature those three groups don't
have any nature and if they said the
meaning of not having any nature is that
they don't have any nature which exists
by definition or nature of existing by
definition do you think there'd be a
problem in this school if they said that
yeah
um
uh now you said there would be a problem
if the mind only School characterized
the meaning of not having a nature is
not having nature of existing by
definition
now does the problem you foresee apply
to all three groups or only to some of
the three groups
that's good it seems like you're
splitting off in a separate mine streams
finally
yeah
uh we'll do a vote in the majority will
win how many you know have a problem how
many groups
let's go
so would there be a problem with
construction
they actually realize the problem but uh
but for the time being you didn't do too
bad and okay don't forget you said there
was no problem
all right
yeah
uh the problem that's gonna arise here
you know you got the easy problem okay
there's another problem arising here
don't forget that we're talking about
the second turning of the wheel the
middle turning of the wheel in which the
Buddha taught the President part of me
to Sutra us in their longer and medium
and briefer forms and don't forget that
in the second turning of the wheel in
the middle turning of the wheel Lord
Buddha specifically said that things
don't exist by definition nothing exists
by definition
so if you go saying that what Lord
Buddha meant when he said things don't
have a nature is that Lord Buddha meant
that things don't have a nature of
existing by definition then you are
going to become a school that has to
accept or agree that the second turning
of the wheel was something literal that
the Buddha was speaking literally when
he taught the secretary of the wheel and
I guess there's going to be a problem
coming regardless
symptoms
and don't forget that since we've shut
the door to majimika the mighty make a
door is shut
that don't forget that according to
remind only school if you're a person
who believes that the secretary of the
wheel was spoken literally you have
fallen into what we call means the
extreme or the the cliff we call the
chasm uh of believing that nothing
exists at all so the minority School
says that if you believe the secretary
of the wheel was spoken literally and
that the Buddha meant what he said then
you have fallen off into the extreme or
the cliff off the cliff of what we call
the extreme of believing that nothing
exists or the things have discontinued
it's called discontinued okay
uh what we're saying by the way when we
say that you have fallen into the
extreme or fallen off the cliff of the
extreme is that uh your Viewpoint or the
way you see things has fallen off the
extreme and you don't have to worry that
somehow your body's gonna fall asleep
it's not that like your physical body is
going to fall off and clearness
version of things that are dependent
things that have causes and you go
saying that those things don't exist by
definition what are you really saying
there
today
if those things become non-existent then
you and me do too
anywhere either
the things which are caused this is the
problem that you would actually be
implying in this school that they don't
exist at all
hi guys
so in the same uh with the same
reasoning if you look at the emptiness
or the young group or the total
existence that exist with regard to a
water pitcher okay and if you said oh it
doesn't have any existence by definition
then you'd be saying it what didn't
exist at all you'd be saying it didn't
exist at all so then you'd lose that
that category as well
uh do you think it becomes non-existent
or not if you say it doesn't exist by
definition in this school
in this school to say that the emptiness
that a vase has or what a picture has
does not exist by definition do you get
in trouble in this school
s
and if uh if emptiness itself becomes
non-existent because you're accusative
being non-existing by definition then a
thing like a water pitcher would not
have an ultimate nature and then No
Object around us would have an ultimate
nature it's Ultimate Reality nothing
around us would have its Ultimate
Reality so that'd be a big problem
nothing would have its own Ultimate Way
of being
so then the uh Ultimate Way the Ultimate
Reality of things would become
um
something that was not the Ultimate
Reality of things
uh then I promised you a problem with
constructs didn't I
yeah
uh you guys aren't so uh you know you
aren't so bad because in the actual
scripture itself at this point a debater
comes and makes the same objection he
says the same thing you know how could
there be a problem then with the
construct
um
and now here the uh somebody comes up
and makes an objection they say the same
thing they say I see how you can have a
problem if you characterize those other
two groups meaning uh dependent things
and emptiness itself as not existing by
by definition but I don't see how you
can have any problem if you described
constructs as non-existing by definition
I don't see any problem there someone
comes and makes the very same statement
that you guys made foreign
foreign
uh okay so with regard to uh constructs
so we're talking about constructs now uh
there are two flavors of constructs uh
there are constructs which really don't
exist okay so for example you can you
can say uh you can imagine a flower that
grows in midair and that's in the flavor
or the category of constructs that don't
really exist the imagination exists but
the flower doesn't exist okay so that
that's one way of describing uh
constructs but then again there are
constructs that uh that form around
objects that we think about so if for
example we're thinking about a vase a
water pitcher and with considering its
qualities we're thinking about the
nature of the of the of the water
pitcher we when we consider an object
like a water pitcher which belongs to
the group called dependent things or
cause things
when we consider it though we have to
immediately start forming a mental
picture about it right what do you guys
think you know when we consider a water
pitcher and we're trying to solve some
problem about it you know isn't it
permanent doesn't have these qualities
doesn't have separate qualities do we or
do we not at that point
with regard to this thing which belongs
to the category of caused things right
category of dependent things are we
forming the mental pictures to
understand it better to think about it
better and even can we do that without a
lot of pitching around just sitting on
our bed considering the qualities of a
water pitcher considering the the
concepts that regard to it that that
relate to a lot of pictures cannot we do
that even just sitting in our bed
considering a mental picture of a water
pitcher
so if we just if if we got to a position
where we were implying that no cost
thing in the world had any existence at
all right
okay so if we reached a position where
we were denying the very existence of
cause things in the universe
then wouldn't we slowly kind of
roundabout way be denying uh the
existence of all those constructs or
thoughts that we have about modern
pictures because there wouldn't be any
water pitches to consider
Ed
so yeah
so if you go around saying that cause
things uh don't have any existence by
definition right then slowly slowly
slowly in an in a gradual roundabout way
you are denying that constructs
themselves have a new existence
uh what do you guys think does it
gradually in a roundabout way you know
start to attack the very existence of
our of our of our imaginations of our
constructs of our constructs if you if
you destroyed all the cause things in
the world oh if you destroyed all the
vases in the world then wouldn't it
start to in a roundabout way start to
destroy all of our the way that we think
about it because you can't think about
it because we can't have a mental image
of it because there aren't any around
um
you know when you wanna
get someone beat up you don't have to
just confront them face to face and hit
them you know you can just talk to some
people send them over there and see what
happens you know and uh you know in a
roundabout way uh it's hurting
constructs too isn't it yeah
uh so I'll give you an example okay uh
if it happened in the world that all
places all locations all dirt right all
Earth uh all places started to be
non-existent you know if they start to
wipe out all the places all all places
on the Earth all dirt on the earth uh
then wouldn't uh in a gradual but very
sure way uh do damage to our stomachs
now in our stomachs and those places
aren't uh no big connection right I mean
the stomachs are one thing places are a
different thing but if somebody wiped
out all the places on this planet would
it gradually do some kind of damage to
our stomachs
yeah it would be the case wouldn't it
you know places are just external far
away things stomachs are internal
intimate things connected to us no real
uh obvious relationship between the two
no real obviously connection between two
between the two but it is certainly the
case that if all the places on this
planet were wiped out then certainly
something would happen to our stomachs
eventually okay
um
foreign
summarizing so we we found that it
wasn't a problem to characterize uh
cause things as having a nature which is
such that they do not exist by
definition and that was no problem there
and it wasn't such a problem to do to
characterize uh what was the other one
uh Ultimate Reality as as having a
nature such that it didn't exist by
definition and we didn't have a problem
with that but when we got to what was
the other one imaginary things
conster and backwards sorry
oh
there's a problem yeah there is a
problem with those two okay you get a
direct problem with emptiness if you
characterize this having nature of
non-existing by definition
and you do get a problem with uh
costings if you characterize them as
having a nature of non-existing by
definition direct problem
but indirectly you get a problem with uh
constructs if you describe them as
non-existing by having not have any
nature of existing by definition you do
get a problem with them uh in a way that
you are according that means you are
implicitly denying their very existence
conduct means to say about something
which does exist that it doesn't exist
so you are you are implicitly uh putting
down or or denying the very existence of
something which which really does exist
if you if you characterize it as
something is having a nature of
non-existing by definition
okay
um
so the fact that if you characterize
this not having a nature as being what
was it not having nature of having by of
existing by definition for all three if
you if you characterized all three that
way uh then there'd be the the same
problem would would uh come for all
three is also backed up by Lord Buddha's
own statement in his own book so from
the mine only point of view uh the
second turning of the wheel uh where the
this is uh
they say that the Buddha says in this
section he says you cannot take what I
said literally and what I meant as being
the same thing okay so we're on the page
16 last line uh Lord Buddha himself says
when I taught the second turning of the
wheel uh you shouldn't take what I said
uh in my speech to be literal there's a
distinction between what I said and what
I meant those are not the same things
how does it apply why shouldn't you do
that Lord Buddha himself says uh you
will fall into the extreme of thinking
things don't exist it's thinking
thinking enough nothing exists and then
Lord Buddha himself says because you
will be thinking that with regard to
each of the three groups and he names
the three groups so you can't go around
saying that it doesn't hurt one group
and it hurts the other two groups or
something like that he says you have to
accept it hurts all three groups not
only because it's logically true in the
way that we just proved in the
roundabout thing but also because
scripturally by scriptural Authority
Lord Buddha himself said if you take
what I said and what I mean to be the
same then you will be falling into the
extreme of thinking that nothing exists
and you because you'll be thinking that
about all three of those groups and
Buddha himself has all three of those
groups
foreign
goes all the way stretches all the way
up to page 18 line two and then gentle
cover goes in again to that point that
you know in the second turn of the wheel
the Buddha said that nothing has a
nature of existing by definition
uh now if you go ahead and start
accepting that he meant what he said and
that uh and you start saying that these
things have when you say that they don't
have a nature you mean they say you mean
to say they don't have a nature of
existing by definition if you start
saying that then you know what you
become a person who is believing or
accepting that the second turning of the
wheel was something that was spoken
literally and that the Buddha said what
he meant and what he meant was what he
said and that they met you you are in
trouble of becoming a person who
believes that what the Buddha said
during the second attorney of the wheel
he meant literally and then according to
you mind only people what
you're saying nothing exists you've
fallen off the cliff you've fallen into
the extreme of saying nothing exists at
all according to your own score okay
uh to to summarize everything that's
being said here you can say it in a very
simple way if dependent things exist if
the group called dependent things exist
then the other two groups can exist too
okay then then there would be the other
two groups so you know if you have any
one of them existing you could say the
other two groups are existing but if you
said of any one group uh for example
dependent things that it didn't have a
narrative existing by definition and
then you and if you said that it didn't
exist therefore then you'd have to be
saying that about the other groups as
well if any one of the necessary three
groups have some ontological status
which is either existing or non-existing
then as a group the three groups are
either broken up or not broken up we can
either exist or can't exist if you start
denying the existence of any one of the
three then as a group they their
validity is is changed and they become
non-existent
it is
oh boy uh we talked about the middle
turning of the wheel the other day and
we said there are certain
characteristics to describe it or
certain different categories or certain
different kinds of things in the
secretary of the wheel how many was that
I'm not asking about the first one
the secretary there were certain
categories and certain or certain uh
certain certain uh characteristics or
certain features that I spoke about
it
uh I wasn't uh concerned so much about
the suffered categories of how many
things it was from physical format on
top but how many characterizations how
many different uh descriptions do we use
to describe those things
things
one guy says five one guy says three I
think you guys would be really good Mo
divination you know you just said roll
them and say oh okay you know
laughs
with a moat you can say two different
things and the same thing happens anyway
that's in the book right that's in your
notebook right that's the main guy here
that's a personal fight
foreign
don't forget that uh existing by
definition is the one that applied to
everything so it didn't really make a
big point about it and then we started
with number two by saying things don't
start from now and that's actually
number two because the the first one
covers on them
say things don't have any
then we said there's a problem with
things that are caused and there's a
problem with emptiness itself didn't we
didn't we just say that
um
so we do have a problem though right I
mean just the basic things we do have a
problem if we characterize things as not
existing by definition right yeah
so this morning the whole thing we did
this morning the whole point of thing we
did this morning is that in the second
turning of the wheel in the middle
turning of the wheel the first
characteristic that Lord Buddha talked
about was that things don't have any
nature of existing by definition and
then we just got through saying that if
you say that about those three groups of
things you have a problem right
and if you go to the second
characteristic the second feature the
second description the Lord Buddha made
during the middle turning of the wheel
which was that things don't start the
starting of things doesn't have a nature
of existing by definition
then you get the same three houses with
the same three groups don't you
thank you
uh so a question for you guys if we take
those three groups of things right uh
constructs changing things or dependent
things and emptiness itself right and
you kick out uh changing things and
emptiness itself and you stick to uh
sorry what was it uh imaginary things or
constructs right if you stick to
constructs in the mind only school if
someone comes along and says it doesn't
have a nature of existing by definition
do you have a problem or don't you have
a problem kick out those other two now
isolate constructs if you say in the
mind only school about constructs that
they don't have a nature of existing by
definition do you have a problem or
don't you have a problem
yeah and that's why you guys originally
said oh two of them have a problem one
of them doesn't have a problem so that's
why you can come now and say well if you
take away those two and just stick to
this one then you don't have a problem
that's why you could say that right
take that whole logic that we just
talked about with those three and
everything I just said and apply it now
to our newer
um
so now if you take the second
characteristic or the second description
that Lord Buddha spoke during the second
turning of the wheel the median turn the
wheel which is that the beginning of
things or the birth of things or the
arising of things or the growing of
things does not exist by definition
and if you kick out
uh things that depend things that grow
and if you're only talking about things
that are constructs and emptiness itself
do you have a problem or don't you have
a problem
uh obviously uh
it's another case of you don't beat the
guy in the face right there you send
guys after him and it hurts him uh you
know by Way by way of things so uh does
it directly do have any problem with
with things that are dependent when you
say that it doesn't have any nature of
growing
by definition
do you have a problem with things that
are dependent things that go there ain't
no time it is
so it's almost the reverse right it's a
reverse image of the other one when a
problem comes about saying it with
regard to things which are caused or
things which are dependent then by
implication or indirectly you start to
have a problem with saying it about
things which are constructs and things
which are emptiness
nothing
if you say something which would
invalidate the existence of things that
are dependent things like come from
causes for example if you say about them
they don't have a nature of starting
but through any uh by by definition then
uh you get an the the indirect Damage
Done to constructs is that the ability
to make a construct the imagination
itself
uh is one of these objects it's one of
those things that's dependence one of
those things that has causes so if you
wipe that one out if you wipe out the
ability to imagine the ability to create
a con construct then you're doing damage
indirectly sort of directly indirectly
to the constructs themselves
what did we say about things that are
dependent do we say they didn't have any
nature uh of existing by definition or
did we say they don't have any nature of
growing by definition
just now
what did we say about it
so so keep that distinction in mind
we're not talking about not having a
nature of existing by definition right
now at this point we're talking about uh
things that are dependent not having a
nature of starting or growing by
definition
uh so uh the the logic here is the same
uh as before uh if if if dependent
things didn't have a nature of growing
by definition so if they therefore
didn't exist at all then the ability to
imagine wouldn't exists either and then
the things which the ability to imagine
imagines wouldn't exist either and you
do damage to the category of constructs
uh so now we go to the third category
what is the third group we're talking
about emptiness itself okay and and
don't forget that every kind of
emptiness has to have something that is
empty it has to apply to a certain
object you have to say this thing has
its emptiness this thing has its
emptiness every kind of existence every
kind of emptiness that exists is an
emptiness that exists with regard to a
basis or with regard to a certain object
so for example when we talk about a
chair then we talk about the emptiness
of the chair The Emptiness of the chair
is the quality that applies to the chair
that is connected to the chair so what
happens what do you guys think happens
if we remove the chair because we denied
that things that are dependent grew by
definition what happens if we wipe out
all those chairs
I like your example of a chair and I did
use the example of a chair but I was
more asking the question of if you wiped
out all the bases plural of emptiness
zoos around the universe then what do
you think would happen
your your idea will help my other
questions
so my question for you is a very more
general question it's a generic question
if you remove the thing which has the
emptiness what happens to the emptiness
since
all those emptinesses
foreign
uh you should have in your mind
we've been talking about what would
happen if you wiped out all the things
which are causing the world and then
their emptiness would go away uh but
don't don't forget we have that first
category to consider which are
constructs right so we didn't mention
constructs
if you wipe out everything that has
causes directly then remember we said
that indirectly you'd be wiping out all
things which are constructed because by
wiping out all things that had causes
you'd be wiping out all the imaginations
that imagine all the things that dream
up all the things that they construct so
really we're we're more talking about
not just the problem that would occur
with all the emptinesses in the world if
you wiped out all the things which are
caused we're talking about a bigger
problem if you wiped out all the things
which were caused and therefore by
implication wiped out all the constructs
then you'd be wiping out all the
emptiness in the universe because you'd
be wiping out the emptinesses that
applied to changing things and you'd be
wiping out all the emptinesses that
applied to non-changing things then
you've got a much bigger problem you're
wiping out a lot more emptiness now
you're wiping out all the emptinesses of
everything if so directly you're wiping
out the emptinesses of things that
change indirectly you're wiping out the
in the the emptinesses of things that
don't change and that's a much bigger
problem
you got it got it
if you take the second characteristic
that was spoken during the middle
turning of the wheel which is that
nothing begins
um nothing has a nature Beginning by
definition then in the minority School
you start to have a direct problem with
things that grow things that have causes
you start to have an indirect problem
with imagine things and then you have a
whole bigger implied the whole the mess
gets bigger with all the emptinesses of
all those things start disappearing
cool you also cannot accept on Face
Value the second statement about you
know during the secretary of the will
and he said that things don't the growth
of things are the beginning of things
doesn't have
foreign
uh that whole spill which I just gave
you is stated here in the text on page
18 uh you go one two three four seven
lines up beginning with the phrases
and going on down to three lines from
the bottom that whole Spiel I just gave
you is expressed in those few lines in
this text okay you can find it there
everything that I just said is right
there and he's saying here are the
problems that would occur if you believe
literally that the Buddha meant what he
said when he said the birth or the
arrival of things and here he says also
the stopping of things uh has a nature
entered existing by definition these are
the problems that would arise if you
believed that was literal in your school
um
and don't forget says Justin copper in
the fourth line from the bottom uh your
school is a school that says that if the
beginning and ending of things didn't
exist by definition then the beginning
and ending of things wouldn't exist at
all since your school that that's your
score right and again he's having that
implication right okay he's rubbing it
in a little bit
uh so I gotta ask a question about to
you guys you know we had this point
before about the 5 five characteristics
of the five descriptions during the
second turn of the wheel and you've done
a good job on that but I have a question
to ask you didn't we organize those into
some kind of groups weren't there any
kind of groups that we organize those
five or did we just talk about the five
individually you know one group of five
or did we organize them into kind of any
kind of separate groupings
uh it's nice to meet an elected official
for a whole group of people
did anybody else also remember that
I couldn't do that you know yeah
love me
he like everyone else is it
answering in one voice he asked the
question he gets 20 ounces back at the
same time
what you say is exactly right yeah and
we had five and we took one out and we
tuned it as a separate group we took
four hours two minutes or something we
came up with two groups you're right
so now on page 18 we're going down and
talking about the fourth she she did one
one yeah
uh so now we get that distinction
between the one and the four and now the
second category by the way the small
letter in there is not part of the
original text that somebody is adding
that uh because the text tends to say
second
somebody has put them in there for you
he says uh there's a question coming up
to just a couple if that's what it means
when we say in a general way that things
don't have any nature meaning any nature
of existing by definition which is the
first of the time right then what how
does that apply to the latter four okay
how does how does your discussion that
you just finished apply to the letter
four
okay of the five characterizations that
occurred during the second training
wheel okay
uh that's the road we'll have to travel
okay
um
we're talking about
when you talk about the path we're going
to travel meaning I think he's closing
up right any and he's saying the path
that we have to travel now is the
question of in the second turning of the
wheel according to the mind only school
who cannot accept it as being literal
who are forced to accept it as not being
literal then what did the Buddha have in
mind what was the Buddha thinking what
was the Buddha's true intent when he
spoke during the secretary of the wheel
about things not having about these four
things I'm not having any nature of
existing by their own and I want to give
you an example of what it means when a
person says something and has a
different thing in mind okay when they
like when they say something that they
that they are saying but they don't mean
it to be taken literally and there's
something else they have in mind that
they're trying to communicate to someone
else so let's take the example you know
I'm a monk we're monks around here let's
take the example of a moment uh now
monks we might have a student you know
there's a teacher has a student and he's
got this kind of a cup on his table and
he's talking to the student assistant
could you go wash that cup out for me
you know and then the student goes over
to the bathroom and you hear him banging
around the sink and then you hear this
big crash and he he dropped the cup he
didn't break the cup okay and then if
the teacher calls out to him and says
excuse me could you break that cup for
me uh the teacher isn't meaning it to be
taken literally right he's he's got some
kind of uh other other message he's
trying to communicate he had a student
okay so that would be a true example
that'd be a good example of the concept
of a person saying something and wanting
to communicate a different message
and the student is thinking
the teacher told me break that cup but
what it means is for you know God damn
it don't break down again
totally opposite they're not here
so uh it's the same thing with the
second turn of the wheel if you are a
person who's sitting in the mine only
school okay if you're a member of the
Mind only school and you're reading
about the secretary of the wheel and
Lord Buddha keeps saying nothing has any
nature in its own nothing has any nature
existing by definition none of these
things have any nature of doing and you
keep hearing says over and over and over
again you begin thinking he must have
something in mind you know he must have
some other Methodist is trying to
communicate to me when he says nothing
has any nation of its own it's just like
the teacher saying don't break it it's
just like the message of don't break it
or break it okay there must be uh some
message some real message that the
Buddha had in mind when he made those
statements about nothing having any uh
nature of having any definitive
existence there must be some message in
mind like the teacher's message of don't
break it okay
which is which is a an implied message
or or the true intention of the teacher
when he says break it and it says break
it what it means is don't break it there
must be some other message that Lord
Buddha was trying to communicate to us
like like in that example
uh how many
how many real messages do you think are
contained in the second turn of the
wheel how many were the real messaging
team is trying to convey what it what
are the real messages that Lord Buddha
was trying to convey during the second
turn in the wheel to a my normal
personality
well when you say the real message
you're applying on my annoying person I
added that because you know when you say
real message you must be speaking from
the point of view of the minority school
because it's only you say the words real
message only when you believe that he
wasn't speaking literally
what was what was he really trying to
communicate how many things was he
really trying to communicate
um
I'm just asking you you know what do you
generally think about it I'm not you
know I don't need a real I'm just let's
just have it what do you say it's an
open question give me an open answer
what are the two that you think
what are the two real messages
uh
um
I shut the door to the middle way we
don't want to go there into the
middleweight room okay stick yourself to
the mind only school what was it that
the Buddha had in mind when he got up
and said nothing has any names of its
own nothing has been mentioned
or give me one
being clever with me you know I asked
you how many and you gave me one
uh predictions
uh you said you thought that what it was
but thinking about what it was is not
quite knowing what it was
just kidding it really is to me
um
you're right that is three uh with the
first one it's sort of exactly what he
said with the first one which is
imaginary objects or constructs it's
exactly what I said they don't have a
narrative existing by definition and so
from the point of view of the first
industry groups yeah what he was saying
when he said they don't have a nature of
existing by definition is pretty much
what he meant meaning that imaginary
obvious don't have a nature of having
any definitive existence okay but then
when he got to the second one and he
said uh things that are dependent or
things that are caused don't have any
nature of growing right don't have any
nature of starting then what he meant is
not I was done they don't have a nature
of not having causes
so when he said they don't have a
natural definition what he meant was not
that they don't have a nature of
existing by definition but they don't
have a nature of a
and then when he said
right emptiness itself when he said it
doesn't have any nature of existing by
definition what he meant was it doesn't
have any nature of existing in the way
of a self-existent self
of existing in the in the manner of the
gotcha it doesn't have any nature of
existing in the way or a thing that
could exist uh on its own by itself
but what he meant was emptiness does not
have a nature of existing in the way
that something would exist in existence
on its own by itself okay in the way
within this school of the ultimate
object which we are denying when we talk
about Infamous that's what he meant okay
when he said about emptiness that he
doesn't have a niche of existence by
definition what he meant was emptiness
doesn't have a nation of existing in the
way of a self-existent date and that's
what he meant okay